Finding Aid for Guy C. Larcom papers, 1956-1973
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Guy C. Larcom papers 1956-1973
Larcom, Guy C., 1913-
85268 Aa 2
Ann Arbor, Michigan, city administrator. Correspondence concerning city business, reports to city council, topical files relating to the operation of city departments and to municipal issues; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
10.3 linear feet
The collection came to the library in two principal accessions, the first in 1980, the second in 1989. Donor No. 6489.
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Guy C. Larcom (1913- ), a Massachusetts native, had attained almost twenty years of experience in government administration when he was appointed first city administrator of Ann Arbor in 1956. A graduate of Medford (Mass.) High School, he graduated from Harvard University in 1933, and subsequently took graduate courses in public administration at Columbia University. Prior to his Ann Arbor appointment, Larcom had filled a variety of administrative positions. During World War II, he was administrator of the Willow Run Housing Program. Later, he served as assistant to the president of the Pennsylvania Economy League, and as consultant to the New Jersey Department of Conservation and Economic Development.
The position of city administrator was a new office created by the passage of the revised Ann Arbor city charter in 1956. Larcom was appointed city administrator by the city council, and he acted as its administrative agent on all city business. Specifically, his responsibilities included directing and supervising the various city departments and offices, preparing budgets for these departments, maintaining a central purchasing office and personnel service for the city, attending council meetings, and advising council and submitting requested reports to council members.
In addition to city responsibilities, Larcom was also a lecturer on state, local and county government at the University of Michigan Journalism Department. He served for a time as trustee of the Michigan Municipal League, and was a member of its Legislative Committee. He was also a delegate to the Southeastern Michigan Council of Governments (SEMCOG). In 1973, Larcom retired as city administrator and assumed the position of executive director of Ann Arbor Tomorrow, a non-profit downtown betterment group. He retired from this position in 1977.
The Guy Larcom collection consists almost exclusively of the files of the city administrator for the period 1965 to 1973. The collection, received in multiple accessions, is arranged into the following series: City Administrator's files; Photographs; and Special Topics.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.). City Administrator.; Ann Arbor (Mich.). Common Council.; Larcom, Guy C.; Municipal government--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Buildings.; Ann Arbor (Mich.). Common Council.; City Hall (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Municipal officials.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- City Administrator's files
  The City Administrator's series (9 linear feet) consists of files received in 1980 and 1989. The earlier accession included incoming and outgoing Correspondence, Speeches, Reports to City Council, and Topical files. The correspondence, broadly defined, also includes inter-office memoranda, as well as citizen requests and complaints, and letters (local, state, and national) on municipal problems and issues. The speeches (to the local Chamber of Commerce and similar groups), often include an evaluation of city government. The Reports to City Council consist of financial statements, official policy decisions, proposals for municipal action, and related action. The Topical files pertain to individual city programs and departments for which Larcom had some responsibility or in which he was deeply interested. Notable files here concern the Ann Arbor Board of Education, the Housing Commission (1971-1972), and the Human Rights Department (1971-1973).
  City Administrator's files received in 1989 were not interfiled with the earlier accession. There is thus some overlap in content. This accession includes an annual report of the city, clippings, correspondence, and speech notes. Much of the correspondence appears to be of a personal nature; however, some city business is covered, involving the Community Systems Foundation and the Water Resources Commission, among other groups.
  - Curriculum vitae (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Outgoing 1965 (Box 1)
    - Incoming 1965 (Box 1)
    - Outgoing January-June 1966 (Box 1)
    - Outgoing July-December 1966 (Box 1)
    - Incoming January-June 1966 (Box 1)
    - Incoming July-December 1966 (Box 1)
    - Outgoing January-June, 1967 (Box 2)
    - Outgoing July-December 1967 (Box 2)
    - Incoming January-April 1967 (Box 2)
    - Incoming July-December 1967 (Box 2)
    - Outgoing January-June 1968 (Box 2)
    - Outgoing July-December 1968 (Box 2)
    - Incoming 1968 (Box 2)
    - Outgoing January-June 1969 (Box 3)
    - Outgoing July-December 1969 (Box 3)
    - Incoming January-June 1969 (Box 3)
    - Incoming July-December 1969 (Box 3)
    - Outgoing January-June 1970 (Box 3)
    - Outgoing July-December 1970 (Box 3)
    - Incoming January-June 1970 (Box 4)
    - Incoming July-December 1970 (Box 4)
    - Outgoing January-June 1971 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous 1972-1973 (Box 4)
  - Speeches, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Reports to City Council
    - 1959-1963 (Box 4)
    - 1965 (Box 4)
    - January-June 1966 (Box 4)
    - July-December 1966 (Box 4)
    - January-June 1967 (Box 5)
    - July-December 1967 (Box 5)
    - 1968 (Box 5)
    - January-June 1969 (Box 5)
    - July-December 1969 (Box 5)
    - 1970 (Box 5)
    - 1971 (Box 5)
    - January-April 1972 (Box 6)
    - May-July 1972 (Box 6)
    - July-August 1972 (Box 6)
    - September-December 1972 (Box 6)
    - January-February 1973 (Box 6)
    - March-April 1973 (Box 6)
  - Topical Files 1958-1973
    - Administrator's budgets for departments 1970-1972 (Box 6)
    - All American Cities awards presentation 1966 (Box 6)
    - Ann Arbor Area Goals Conference 1966 (Box 6)
    - Ann Arbor Board of Education (Box 6)
      (folder 1)
    - Ann Arbor Board of Education (Box 7)
      (folder 2)
    - Ann Arbor City Hall (Box 7)
    - Ann Arbor Civic Theater 1961-1965 (Box 7)
    - Archdiocese contract 1969 (Box 7)
    - City-township relations committee (Box 7)
    - Council of Governments 1970 (Box 8)
    - Day care centers 1969-1972 (Box 8)
    - Department of Traffic Engineering and Transportation 1971-1972 (Box 8)
    - Development Committee 1967-1970 (Box 8)
    - Economic Opportunity 1964-1965 (Box 8)
    - Five Year Projection Plan 1971/1972-1976/1977 (Box 8)
    - Governor's Commission on Local Government 1970-1972 (Box 8)
    - Highway Safety 1967 (Box 8)
    - Housing 1971-1972 (Box 9)
    - Human Rights Department 1971-1973, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - International City Managers Association (ICMA); Pittsfield Township; Office of Economic Opportunity 1968 (Box 9)
    - Michigan State Highway Department 1958-1962 (Box 9)
    - Planning Commission Minutes January-August 1973 (Box 9)
    - Politics in conservation (Box 9)
    - Purchasing bids 1972-1973 (Box 9)
    - Southeast Michigan Council of Government (SEMCOG) (Box 9)
  - Annual Report, City of Ann Arbor 1970-1971 (Box 10)
  - Clippings
    - 1956-1957 (Box 10)
    - 1959-1961 (Box 10)
    - 1962 (Box 10)
    - 1966-1973 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence
    - 1956-1957 (Box 10)
    - 1959-1965 (Box 10)
    - 1966-1971 (Box 10)
    - 1971
      - Incoming January-June 1971 (Box 10)
      - Incoming July-December 1971 (Box 10)
      - Outgoing July-December 1971, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - 1972 (Box 10)
    - 1972-1973 (Box 10)
  - Speech Notes 1966-1973, 3 folders (Box 10)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series (0.1 linear feet) provides relatively good coverage of city council members from 1956 to 1973. Other subjects include Old City Hall, New City Hall (1963), participants in the North Campus agreement (1956-1957), the Ann Arbor All-American City Award Banquet (1967), and the Michigan Public Transportation Council (1973).
  - 1956-1973, 6 folders (Box 10)
- Special Topics
  Special Topics includes material received from other individuals interested in preserving documentation of Larcom's career as City Administrator. From Susan Wineberg came files relating to Housing Commission/Urban Renewal. These files date from the mid-1960s and include photographs of city residences scattered throughout the appraisal reports. From Louisa Pieper came additional photographs and volumes of records pertaining to the North Central Urban Renewal Project.
  - Housing Commission/Urban Renewal
    - Housing Commission record book July-December 1967 (Box 10)
    - Urban Renewal Appraisal Reports 1958, 2 volumes (Box 10)
      (includes photographs of the properties under consideration for urban renewal)
    - First Reuse Appraisals, North Central Urban Renewal Project; Part I, Application for Loan & Grant, 1 volumes (Box 11)
    - East Ann Arbor (Pittsfield Village) street name changes, etc. 1964-1968 (Box 11)
    - Public Housing 1968 (Box 11)
    - Urban renewal miscellanea (Box 11)
    - Colored Welfare Building 1967 (Box 11)
  - North Central Urban Renewal Project, 4 volumes (Box 11)
- Photographs
  - Old City Hall, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Mayors and Council (Box 11)